ORIOL VINYALS: Amazing.
Great.
So it's great to be
back at Berkeley.
There was a
probabilistic trip, which
would have helped me
to be in the US today.
But sadly, I took it
very short last week.
So I was in the Bay
last week but not this
week, so we'll have
to do this online.
But yeah, it's great
to be virtually back.
I have deep roots in
Berkeley, as you might know,
if you have known
me for a while.
And today, I mean, this lecture
really will have two parts.
And it's a [? medal, ?]
actually, in a way.
And it's also kind
of, selfishly, I'm
doing this also to remind,
I mean, first and foremost,
people in the field that
lots of ideas recirculate.
And so, in a way, I put
together this slide deck,
or I recovered the slide deck,
from the AlphaStar project,
which is six or so
years old, and realized
that many of the current issues
but also solutions that we're
using in modern LLMs
trace back further before.
But I mean, we did encounter
many of these issues
ourselves when we work
on a fairly, probably
our most advanced, even today,
especially on video games, agent
that DeepMind had
built at the time.
And I'll get into
details now in a second.
But it's useful to revisit
these ideas to see them
with perspective
and also realize
what are the things that we did
back then that, currently, we
can't do, or we're not quite
doing at the same level in LLM.
So this lecture will be a bit
of a mixture between AlphaStar
and also Gemini and
other LLM agents
but with the kind of hindsight,
foresight lens, which hopefully,
you will find entertaining.
So let's go through
a bit of basics.
Now of course, I'm sure you've
covered many of these topics.
And you probably know
them because they
become quite mainstream.
But indulge me into giving
you my own perspective
and point of view.
So this is the OG slide
of DeepMind, actually.
The pitch slide
deck had a version
of this that did
not have StarCraft,
but it had agent environment,
agent with goals, observations,
and actions.
That was, at the time,
not that mainstream.
Reinforcement learning
wasn't mainstream
when DeepMind was
eventually acquired.
And also, it serves
a little bit to try
to put our heads on what is
an agent since this class is
about agents.
And I think today if you ask
people, like, is this an agent,
is this an agentic
behavior, you probably
get quite a few
different answers.
Back then, things were
a bit simpler, though.
We were mostly connecting
to single environments
with, well, [? spect ?]
and defined observations
and actions.
And the agent had just,
maximize reward as a goal.
Of course, in games,
many times, the reward
was fully specified and
fairly simple to compute.
And then this was the loop
that agents lived in forever.
And their goal was
to optimize reward.
Now today, things
are a bit different.
Besides, I guess, having agents
in the traditional sense,
we have assistants
that assist users.
So then, what is the
environment, what
are the actions, start
to be a bit more diffuse.
And I think embracing
that is fine.
This is probably
the most accurate,
at least from our
side, perspective
of what we mean by agents.
So you might be a user of a
chatbot or advanced system.
And you're going to interact
with something, this object.
We can call this the agent.
And as a user, you'll ask
questions, maybe give feedback,
et cetera, et cetera.
And then this agent now
actually is more complex.
In a new way, I think
it's more useful to think
about the environment being
part of the whole package.
So you'll get an
agent harness that's
controlling how you call
the LLMs to issue an action
or issue a search or issue a
terminal command, et cetera,
to this very rich
environment that
could be a digital computer,
a network of computers.
It could be anything.
It could be a game, of
course, as well, very general.
And then that's how we
orchestrate the whole thing.
So it doesn't quite fit
the paradigm as neatly.
But that actually things--
makes it more exciting.
So sometimes when I'm
presenting some of the results
and observations,
especially from AlphaStar,
it's going to come from a
more simplistic world, where
single environment, clearly
defined, and no user, so
to speak.
So the world has changed.
And these will keep
evolving, especially
as we get to an exciting
topic that, I think,
is the one I want
to leave you, maybe
with some
thought-provoking ideas
and observations on
multi-agent systems,
and what does that
even mean here.
So a bit of history.
The DeepMind, at the
time of acquisition,
had just mastered Atari.
I remember fondly
the NeurIPS in which
Vlad presented the results.
And they felt really refreshing.
I believe that was the
sequence-to-sequence in NeurIPS.
Maybe it was the year before.
I can't remember.
It was a while ago.
And then in the internal
program for DeepMind,
there was sort of a curriculum
of difficulty of games
that we were going to tackle.
And famously, Go came a
few years after Atari.
And then I would
say, maybe StarCraft
graduated as to just master
all due to its complexity.
Although, of course, there's
many interesting games
that have slightly
different complexities.
But StarCraft, clearly for
AI, felt like a good kind
of ending note.
Although even today, we
are working on games still,
as you might have seen with
things like WOT models.
And SEMA 2.0 was just released
that can play 3D games
and so on.
But the approach
is quite different.
Now, blast from
the past as well.
So 2011, ages ago, I used
to be a grad student.
And very exciting
from Dan Kline's group
was this project that tried
to tackle solving StarCraft
with machine learning.
And there was a whole
class set for testing,
kind of maybe somewhat
good, old-style-fashion AI,
although some machine
learning as well,
interleave with just
trying to play the game
or play different
aspects of the game.
So it was recognized,
of course, as a domain.
And personally, of course,
this resonated very much
when I saw DeepMind for
the first time applying
ML, which I love, to video
games, which I love--
I used to play StarCraft--
to eventually become the lead
of the AlphaStar project.
So very, very interesting
domain at the time.
In 2011, really, it
seemed quite impossible
that a single neural
net could play the game.
But that's basically
what we did.
And for those of you who
do not know StarCraft,
I mean, it's very hard to give
you a two-minute overview.
But it's essentially a
chess in which you don't
see the board all the time.
And things are fairly
continuous, like actions.
It's a real-time strategy game.
So there's lots of hiding
information from the enemy
because it's
partial, observable.
And generally, the action
space is quite complex
because you have to control
not only the strategy
at the high level but
also the microstrategy
about how to move your
units about the map.
So here you have a map.
It has resources.
You gather resources.
You get money.
You build buildings.
You build units.
You engage the enemy.
And if you destroy all
the enemy buildings,
that's the winning
or losing condition.
So it's kind of a fun game.
It's been quite heavily
played over the years,
different versions of it.
And it brought esports to life
in South Korea, certainly very,
very early days, in
the late 1990s even.
So this kind of
pioneered, in a way also,
certain aspects of video gaming.
Different points of
view, this is the one
you might have actually seen
that's rendered directly
from the game.
This is your UI.
you only see on the bottom
left here, part of the map.
You need to move the camera,
send the units around, build
buildings, issue commands.
It's fairly fast-paced.
So there's lots of
cool subproblems
that you could tackle
as an AI domain.
But as I was saying, what
we actually end up doing--
and I'll describe bits and
pieces but not in full--
we trained a single
neural network, basically,
that was issuing all
these commands and how
and it matters to LLM or current
trends that we're seeing.
I'll describe in the
second part of the talk.
And then in the third part,
we'll cover multi-agent.
So achievement wise,
I mean, it was fun.
And I remember
fondly when our agent
achieved grandmaster
status, which
is given only to the top 100
players in any given region.
So we were playing online,
literally in our office.
So imagine playing
video games at work.
That was pretty fun.
And we were all sitting around,
playing games against people
that didn't know they were
playing against AlphaStar,
although many could guess.
And there was lots
of speculation
because you had to opt in to
play against possibly advanced
AIs.
But eventually, we reached
the grandmaster milestone.
And then later, we also
went sort of in the wild
in BlizzCon, which is a NeurIPS
for StarCraft, so to speak,
where we played
many, many folks who
just were mesmerized by playing
against an AI at the time.
This was, I believe,
our first AI system
in the wild from
DeepMind, actually.
So it was quite nice to
just interact with people,
see how they felt about
the game, AI, et cetera.
This was 2019, right
before the pandemic hit.
And so we visited this
wonderful, very different style,
conference, I would
say than NeurIPS,
although I think NeurIPS is
becoming a bit like this as well
lately.
And it was fun.
We played a bunch
of people, including
Serral, who was one of
the legends of the game.
If you want to see the games,
the five games we played,
I believe YouTube links
are here at your disposal.
You can see here,
me, a bit tense
to see what the agent would
do under such strong opponent.
But it was all fun.
And I think probably the
most profound realization
was a couple of
weeks after, you see,
November 24, Serral
mentioned that he actually
copied StarCraft or AlphaStar,
one of the [INAUDIBLE]
that he had played against.
And of course, an obvious
comment that, again, in a way,
concluded this epoch we had
at DeepMind on mastering games
in one-on-one setting, was
that we got a player learning
from AlphaStar.
But of course, AlphaStar
had learned from several,
as you will see in a second.
So that was pretty fun.
So let's start to see, maybe
some obvious, some less obvious,
connections.
And then yeah, basically,
why does it all make sense?
Even when we talk to reporters
at the time, very early days,
they didn't
understand the impact
of playing games in real world.
So here I try to map,
fairly imperfectly,
the timeline of certain major
projects, Alpha asterisk
projects, if you will,
that kind of, in a way,
took inspiration, either
algorithmically or learnings
or whatnot, from the
previous projects that
had come in because games
were such a good sandbox
to try some ideas to
scale up neural networks.
And I mean, at the time, it
was a bit hard to convey this
to, maybe, general public.
But it's great to see that
this kind of plan for, really,
the whole company was set
about, is taking shape.
And games still have a
role to play, by the way,
into building, pursuing
AGI in the context of LLMs.
But here, there's
a few projects.
I didn't put all of them.
Certainly, there's no
Atari, for example.
But certainly, as I
mentioned, after Go,
we decided to tackle StarCraft.
And then there's no other games.
But after that, we
had huge inspiration
to start working on coding
early days on our first LLMs--
Chinchilla.
Visual language models
Flamingo or Gato.
And AlphaFold also took
inspiration of, I mean,
certain aspects of transformers,
distillation of data, et cetera.
And today, as you
probably can guess,
a lot of the research and
resources are now heavily
invested into a single
project, almost,
although it's very
large-- so there's many,
many different components--
called Gemini, which I'm
co-tech leading, together
with Jeff and Noah.
And of course, in
there, we're just
trying to build the most
general system we can.
So a game or playing
a single game
might be one of the many, many
things, the incredible things
that these models can do today.
But it's nice to also look back
and attribute a bit of ideas
or where things come from.
So more specifically, let's dive
into some technical details.
And some have striking
closeness, I would say,
with how today we're creating
some of these amazing LLMs.
So this is from the Nature paper
that was eventually published.
And we'll discuss
the three aspects.
But in sequence,
we did, basically,
three things to create
this single neural network.
We had, first,
supervised learning,
as we called it in this figure,
learning from human data.
Then we had a step of
reinforcement learning.
And this reinforcement learning
didn't happen in a vacuum.
It happened in a massive
multi-agent system,
like as follows.
So mapping to today's
projects or work,
this is what we commonly
now call pre-training.
This is post-training.
And I don't think
there's a massive amount
of [? motivation ?]
work, although there
is more and more, of course,
as we get more mature
in the technology for LLMs.
But even at the
highest level of how
the different steps of
creating this agent,
we already could
see, or we already
can see that many
of the problems
we faced back then apply today.
And you will see why
in more detail now
for each of these stages.
So let's start with actually
something that at the time
felt kind of complicated
and also, in a way,
obvious in hindsight, having
worked on sequence models, which
is, how to deal with
actions, the actions
that you needed to
issue to activate
or to operate StarCraft.
So the actions were fixed.
There was an API.
And as an API, you basically had
all sorts of different functions
that you could call.
And different functions
required different arguments.
So this is basically
an API that Blizzard
has and had before we started
working with them already
to interact or to send
network messages, actually,
between players in StarCraft.
And we just used it as is.
So you could imagine
in this instance,
there's this thing here
that blocks this ramp.
So there's an action
called forcefield,
which is the name of this thing.
And you issue this action
to this set of units.
So you're saying,
hey, set of units,
try to issue a forcefield
in these coordinates, 6, 82.
And then you also say,
delay from current.
You can wait 10 steps, which
is kind of half a second
or something.
And only repeat
this action once.
So that's how you do
everything in the game.
And it was a bit tricky
to how would we be
able to issue these commands.
So the solution we
found is to just lay out
an autoregressive model, a kind
of a little recurrent neural
network that was structured so
that all these arguments were
lining up with different
softmaxes, that would basically
say, Q, yes or no, when.
And then it's a softmax
between 0 and 128 steps
or whatever maximum
we decided, what
is also softmax, a categorical
softmax, over positions,
et cetera, et cetera.
So we handcrafted
this architecture.
And then we obviously learned
both imitation and reinforcement
learning to finesse how to issue
these sequence of instructions
or commands that form
an API call that then we
would send to the game.
And this is strikingly close
to tool use in general.
Because in tool use
in LLMs, what we
have is an access to an API.
There's MCP.
There's so many
different protocols.
But essentially, there's an API.
There's a way to define
how to call a search engine
or issue a command
on a terminal,
or click on the screen for
that matter, all these things.
And then this is defined
now in natural language.
But actually, lots of different
problems and solutions,
again, align here.
And it was cool too.
At the time, I mentioned
when I talk about AlphaStar,
AlphaStar is like a language.
You just need to issue
these, literally,
code calls or API
calls into the game.
And there are some differences
that are notable as well.
Here, this architecture
is setting the API.
So the aggressive
actions are expressed
through this particular
architecture.
As cool as it is, it's fixed.
Whereas today, we know that
to issue API calls using
the power of generalization of
text or code or combinations
allows us to issue
API calls to all sorts
of different environments that
agents might be connected to.
We also have now a single
transformer architecture
that just writes these
text or code for us that
then is interpreted and
sent to the environment.
And then there's actually
a lot of flexibility even
in the formats because you can
instruct the models to change
the formats if you want to be
empirical about which formats
might be best, versus
here, where there's
a certain architectural
rigidity then.
So of course, we did
ablate many decisions.
And we had to retrain the
models and then try which
ones play the game better.
But it was much more cumbersome
if we need to retrain.
Now another very
big problem, and I
think this is actually a
key debate, even today.
It's still pretty hot
between many folks, which
are, the issue of using
imitation learning, which
we commonly denote as
pre-training in the LLM world.
So in StarCraft, unlike,
let's say, Go or Atari,
where the action
space, however large,
was literally not as large
as it is in StarCraft,
where it's very combinatorial,
and also the time horizon
was much longer, et
cetera, et cetera,
exploration is and
was very challenging.
And I'll demonstrate that
kind of pretty sharply
in the next video.
So the problem is, random
policy will not do much
in this game that's useful.
And so in a way, the
bitter lesson discussion,
which is, should you gather
as much imitation learning
experience to bootstrap the
knowledge about the domain
even in a game like
StarCraft, which arguably,
is not AGI complete,
as complex as it is,
didn't work to the
best of our abilities.
So for us, it was very clear
we would need an imitation
learning plus then an experience
learning, reinforcement
learning, loop on top.
And that was kind of a nice
merging of deep learning
and reinforcement learning,
which I very much welcome also
in LLMs, although it can be
debated whether, ultimately,
pure reinforcement
learning, for example,
could get us all the way there.
I strongly believe
that answer is no,
as you can probably guess.
So what happens when you apply
pure reinforcement learning is
that it actually
discovers how to beat
the enemy but in a way
that is unsatisfactory.
It takes all your workers.
And then it just
sends them to attack.
This is not an
uncommon technique.
I mean, if you're a
newbie, you might do it.
Some professional gamers do it
at some point with [? aliens, ?]
especially that they also bring
all the workers to attack.
This one beat the hardest AI
in the game by exploiting it,
basically with
something that was not
pre-programmed to
defend very well
against this kind of attack.
But clearly, we just kept
seeing these results.
And we had to resort
to essentially using
human data, which
luckily, we did.
We open-sourced over 1
million games of StarCraft,
thanks to Blizzard collecting
anonymous replays online.
They're still available
today, hopefully.
And there's a good
cool way to do research
on imitation learning.
But basically, getting
lots of human data online
was felt necessary and
was part of the solution.
And then something else we
did which also, at the time,
felt very different.
But besides saying, hey,
imitate every human move
from these millions of
games, we also said,
look, hold on a second,
from the whole game,
we know what happened.
We know how good
the players were.
We have some metadata.
We know what the players
eventually built,
what units they did.
So these metadata, we
decided to encode it.
It's a bit of a
cheating information
because, as you
start the game, you
don't know the future units
that will appear, et cetera.
But it was sort of
a guiding signal
to condition the
neural network to look
at these for correlations.
So for instance, the neural
net would, OK, I need to do--
this kind of unit will appear.
It would learn the correlation
between these units and then
how to build it even in
imitation learning setting,
even though the correlations
are fairly weak.
And so that was kind
of a powerful thing
to do for many reasons.
And I'll go get back to these
conditioning signals again
as well during the lecture.
But again, contrasting
this with current LLMs,
this actually was a form of
prompt or instruction following.
So we all start a model, and we
tell it what we want it to do.
And that was our way, without
obviously knowing about this
yet, of doing the same to
a fairly complex system.
We would tell this
agent to either do
this sequence of buildings
and/or to construct these units
and/or to behave like a
professional gamer or a novice
in advance.
That was our instruction.
And then by doing
this, the agent
was reconfigurable to play
in many different styles,
controlled by the user,
prompted by the user.
Now that's a similarity,
many differences.
I mean, this agent was trained
on about 5 billion tokens.
We know, of course, LLMs trained
on over 1 trillion tokens.
So the order of magnitude
is quite different.
These prompts were
structured, were again
hand-tuned to the style
of vectors, binary vectors
that we expected, rather than
expressed through language.
It was not that we were
writing, hey, build an overlord
and then build a [INAUDIBLE].
These were binary
encoded, so to speak.
And then these prompts,
unlike in today's LLMs,
were derived by just
looking at the whole game.
We could look at the future.
We saw the whole game.
We summarized it into
these vectors that
were given from the first frame
of the game versus, of course,
in current LLMs,
oftentimes, we have a prompt
or an instruction that requires
human annotation in some form.
Not always, but it's generally,
hey, there's coding competition.
Someone comes up with a
nice coding competition
problem with some instructions.
And then we let the
agents try to solve
for that particular coding
problem, for example,
or a theorem proved
by LLMs, et cetera.
So again, some similarities,
some differences here as well.
But with these, we actually went
from that state of degeneracy
of RL to actually being able
to start to see believable game
states being achieved
by these agents
that they didn't
experience the game,
but they imitated
the human knowledge,
same as what we see
with LLMs before we
do any post-training step.
Now on to, I think, a very
exciting area of progress,
and I would say
probably not the most
mature even in LLMs, despite
all the investment, which
is post-training or using
reinforcement learning.
So in StarCraft, we did a
few things, all of which,
actually, we also see
in some form or another,
done for similar
reasons, to be honest,
in current large
language models.
So here is a fairly imperfect
way to measure Elo scores.
You might be now fairly familiar
with Elo scores, thanks to LMCs,
for example, which
scores, of course,
your favorite LLM providers
against each other.
But of course, I mean,
chess and many other games
use Elo as a system.
And think of things like 40 Elo
differences, not super large,
but it starts to be significant.
400 is fairly
significant difference.
So if we train from
scratch without human data,
we didn't get a
very strong agent.
Just the supervised learning
policy was at 900 Elo.
So that's a fairly
strong initial state
to then kickstart the whole
reinforcement learning
multi-agent system that we had.
Now, the obvious thing
is that this policy,
initialize it, and
then add, just use
reinforcement learning vanilla,
and you get a bit of a boost.
But what tends to
happen is, you might
see some collapse of
behaviors, which also
is quite commonly seen in LLMs.
So the diversity of
the whole distribution
that you've gathered
over imitation learning
is lost, so to speak.
So we added a
supervised KL penalty,
which is a fancy way to
say, we distill the policy,
the original
policy, onto the one
we were training with
reinforcement learning.
So in a way, you don't
overcommit too early
to a certain particular
way of playing.
You keep the diversity of styles
and strategies, et cetera,
although that itself
was not easy to do.
So we'll get back
to that in a second.
But that helped quite a bit
keep things much better.
So that boosted Elo by 400.
And then the last
thing, which is
this conditioning,
explicit conditioning,
on the kinds of things we want
the agents to do, further boost
the Elo score by
almost 150 or so.
So all these aspects
came together.
And we see obviously all these
being employed as well in LLMs.
Another trick we
find, which was neat,
is that for the value function,
which tells you whether you're
winning or losing, even though
it's a partial observable game,
we found that the value
function seeing the whole board,
so to speak, was
much more accurate
and helped reducing variance in
training, which was problematic
and always using
reinforcement learning.
So that's another trick we did,
which also, in different shapes
and forms, is seen as
positive when you apply it
to certain domains in current
large language models.
So all these tricks and more
are used in modern LLMs.
But what are the differences
between what we were doing here
and LLMs?
I mean, most
crucially, that rewards
can't be fully specified
always, means StarCraft,
you win, you lose.
There are interesting things.
StarCraft, actually, many
people resign before losing.
So it's not that
all the data, you
will get to the winning
condition necessarily.
So there are some
fun problems there.
But by and large, you can
compute success or not success.
Whereas, of course in LLMs,
I mean, write me a nice poem,
it's just good luck, getting
humans to agree on that.
So it's very, very tricky
to reward behaviors
when you're going to much
more general problems.
Now, that's kind of
annoying, definitely
to me, which is, compute
envelope for LLMs
are heavily skewed
towards pre-training.
So you spend most of our
flops in pre-training
and only a little
bit in post-training.
And that feels wrong for
a variety of reasons.
And certainly for AlphaStar,
it was not an exception.
Most of the compute, most
of the weights updates
were done in these experiential
or reinforcement learning stage.
And then overfitting
is very common in LLMs
because, it turns out, we do
not have an infinite amount
of tasks that are
interesting for humans
to solve or to perform that
would help train LLMs when they
deploy it against real
humans or with real humans
in the loop, the kinds
of things they would ask.
There's a limited
amount of data.
Whereas, for StarCraft,
every game is unique.
And because it's constrained
by the environment,
you don't see this
overfitting issue,
which of course is related.
Second and third bullet
points here are quite related.
So let me take a sip of my tea.
And let's get into slightly
more technical, more intuitive
part of the talk about why do
we need multi-agent systems.
What did we do in AlphaStar?
So this was quite
fun at the time.
Certainly, I enjoyed, of
course, the imitation learning.
Sequence-to-sequence
was an example
of imitation learning
very heavily.
Reinforcement learning, I kind
of, hey, I know what's going on.
As a scientist, you learn
you learn that domain
as you join DeepMind.
So it was kind of everywhere.
Multi-agent, all that I
learned was during the project.
And it was very fun and very
intuitive and very simple
to see results, very drastic
results very quickly,
just by trying, sometimes,
extremely simple ideas.
So why did we want multi-agent
learning in AlphaStar,
was to add robustness.
So hopefully,
you'll get what that
means through my explanations.
So you have these models.
They do amazing things.
But we see them fail often.
And that happened
certainly in AlphaStar.
And we see this happen in
LLMs all the time as well.
You ask simple questions,
like, is this number larger
than this number, how
many Rs are in strawberry.
And these models tend to
flop quite dramatically, even
though they might be, I mean,
fuels [? medal ?] levels
in some aspects of mathematics.
They might fail miserably
in other aspects.
So notionally, that is very
similar to the kinds of issues
we encounter.
We train a very good policy
with imitation learning
and reinforcement learning.
We then play the game as
humans, not in the self-play way
that you keep getting
better Elo scores.
And then we found that simple
strategies made the agent--
it didn't react properly.
And they were fairly simple.
If you played at
the high level, it
would really react to your
moves and feel super human.
But it would not
understand some basics.
So it very much
feels similar too.
Although of course,
we're doing a lot
of advancements in our
LLMs, but it felt similar.
And using game
nomenclature, although you
appreciate this is similar to
the failures you're seeing.
We have different policies
or different examples
that we could get
against our agents from--
some are very exploitative,
not that interesting,
to actual strategies
that we would certainly
encounter if we had this
agent online in the wild.
So adversarial policies,
these would be,
like, making the agent flip.
It's almost like
adversarial examples.
In neural nets, you change
a pixel a little bit,
and a panda becomes an airplane,
according to a neural net.
Similar things you can get
with a policy, where maybe you
bring a unit, and you
move it in certain ways,
and the neural network
just degenerates.
So that's unlikely to be found
unless you let, of course,
users probe it.
But it's still the
most basic exploit
you could think about from a
neural network perspective.
Then we have exploiters that
are just repeatedly playing
properly, so to speak,
against a single policy.
But eventually, they
might find a weakness.
And then they go deep
into that weakness,
strategically speaking, up
until they just basically
beat you all the time.
And that's, in a way, similar.
Both exploiter
and the next level
are similar to what we're
seeing in LLMs these days.
The third level is cheese,
which is a strategy that
might generalize, might
be actually fairly robust
against many different opponents
versus the second one, which
is against just one opponent.
But of course, it's not probably
the best optimal strategy
for this game, although
mix and matching cheese
and normal policies is commonly
done at the professional level
of StarCraft as well
because you always
need to be worried that
this strategy might
occur at any time.
You're not seeing the
board all the time.
So to play the game
optimally, similar to,
of course, things
like you see in poker,
you always need to be
worried about many things.
So you cannot go too far into
optimizing against an opponent
that, even though you're not
seeing what they're doing,
you don't know they're doing, so
unpredictability is important.
So the third kind,
the cheeses, you
usually see them at
even the highest level.
And then there's normal
policies and optimal policies.
Now, putting it
differently, this
is called non-transitiveness.
What this means is,
would this policy
work against a
different opponent?
So the adversarial
thing, most likely not.
The adversarial attack might
be specific to the weights
of your neural network.
Then the exploiter policy, you
train or you repeatedly play
against the same opponent, who
cannot update their weights.
So that one is specific
to one opponent.
Cheese tends to generalize.
So maybe when we're talking
about the R's in strawberry
and so on, we see many models,
trained not very differently
but somewhat differently
by different companies,
have these weaknesses.
So maybe, those
kind of exploits are
more in this cheese
category, which
are reasonably generalizable
but, of course,
not very kind of
interesting or strong.
I mean, no one, hopefully, just
uses these to cheese the model,
so to speak.
Then we have normal policies
and then the optimal policy,
which, of course,
is very, very hard
to find with deep reinforcement
learning and multi-agent.
So if we put this
figure differently,
one observation that
my colleague did
is that most interesting games
have these different axes.
The z-axis here is the
strength, the inherent strength
of the player, the Elo
score, or the z-score.
But then within a
slice of this thing,
you would actually
find different cycles
of non-transitivity,
meaning that three models
at the same Elo score,
especially if the Elo score is
not very high, might beat
each other in a way that's
non-transitive.
Rock, paper, scissors
cycles, actually,
that's a commonly used
abstraction that's very clear.
Rock, paper, scissors,
one beats the other.
So think of, we might have
three models, three agents,
at the same level, but one
very strongly beats the next,
and the next one very strongly
beats the next one, and so on.
So there's these cycles
of non-transitive and many
interesting games studied
here possess this property.
And this is obviously
designed for zero-sum games.
So for LLMs, you need to
make some abstractions
to think about what that means.
But we certainly
have Elo scores.
And we certainly see
models having strengths
that are not uniformly
the same across the same,
let's say, level of LMC's
performance, for example.
So that is an interesting aspect
of the complexity of the kind
of task we're trying to solve.
I'll skip this slide.
Just there's the
reference from 2020.
But that explains
this intuitively,
this issue of,
there's an area where
you're not so good, that
things are very non-transitive.
And then as you become
very, very good,
then there's a dominant
strategy that no one can beat.
So that's how we're
seeing in most
games, this kind of behavior.
Now switching gears a
bit, how do you actually
train these models?
There's a few techniques.
But all of them
have some issues,
especially as the games
become strategically complex.
So here is rock, paper,
scissors, actually.
So each of the vertices here
are rock, paper, or scissors.
A strategy is just
a distribution
of what will you play.
So if you play against an
opponent that always plays rock,
well, that's a
very bad strategy.
And the optimal
strategy is uniform.
So if you do self-play kind of
naively, and you try to say,
I'm going to learn an agent that
plays rock, paper, scissors,
you see this effect of
oscillating around the middle,
and locally, you're very
strongly into one strategy.
So sadly, that makes
convergence very hard.
Now, what you can start
thinking about is,
hey, let's add population,
populations of policies
all playing against each other.
So there's several
ways to do this.
Here are the three figures.
But these are starting to feel a
bit better, intuitively as well.
if
I want to learn proactively
rock, paper, scissors,
I'm exposed to many
players, maybe someone who
has very suboptimal strategy
playing only scissors,
but at least, I wouldn't
know that player a priori.
So I might learn,
eventually, that I
have to play the
optimal or the Nash
here, which is the middle
point, equal distribution
of the symbols.
Very simple game, though,
so obviously very toy.
And different strategies
yield different results.
The one that is most hopeful,
but even in this toy example,
it doesn't quite get always
the result that is desired,
is the rightmost,
which is, you have
a population of these agents
that you play against,
and you play always against
the strongest opponent.
That feels like a good
strategy to maybe set yourself,
your whole system up.
And we didn't quite
do this in StarCraft.
But there's a lot
of these intuitions
that played a big role.
Let's see this played.
We saw this.
This is a real
example of what we
saw as we trained
using self-play
in AlphaStar in the early days.
And let's use a
equivalent of rock, paper,
scissors in StarCraft world,
which is three different kinds
of units-- void ray, which
is an air unit; immortal,
which is a very strong ground
unit that cannot attack the air;
and then stalker, which is
kind of a unit that can attack
the air but is not the
strongest ground unit.
So void ray beats immortal,
immortal beats stalker,
stalker beats void ray.
And it's kind of true, if
you do it just naively,
you just build lots
of these units.
You most likely will see this.
This actually represents the
game reasonably faithfully,
so great.
We set this.
And we start from
imitation learning.
So we have that players--
I mean, there's a distribution
over different strategies
that people will have done
when they play online.
And our initial policy
is in the middle.
It's not very good
at either of these.
But it represents the
whole distribution.
And as we trained, what
happened is, our policies,
even with the distillation
losses and so on,
started to only do void rays
really well, lots of them.
Very good micromanagement, but
they became really, really,
really specialized.
So the whole population,
which was not really
a population, this is just
pure self-play actually,
the only strategy that became
present during training
was void rays.
And of course, that washed out
a little bit the prior knowledge
that we came in, even
with distillation.
And that meant that from
the agent's perspective,
it was delusional.
It was playing against itself,
void ray versus void ray,
great battles,
awesome games, that we
recorded during that time.
If the enemy happened to
do immortals, no issue.
These units dominate this.
But if someone
just said, OK, I'm
going to do these
other units, then
these agents didn't even
encounter these anymore
because all it saw
in its games were
massive amounts of void rays.
So sadly, this was not
a very robust strategy.
I mean, if you force
a pro player to, hey,
you have to do
void rays, only do
that, no cheese, no
different strategies,
then this agent was very good.
But of course, people are
diversifying what they do.
These are not the
only three strategies.
There's early rushes,
all sorts of things
that happen in these domains.
So that really didn't work well.
What we added, though, the
key notion in the league
is to add exploiters.
So as you train the model, the
main agent, this steal agent,
it might still specialize
to the void rays.
But then at some point
during the training process,
like the reinforcement
learning, you're
going to add a second agent.
And this agent is going
to be an exploiter,
meaning that it's
only going to care
about beating this agent here.
Its goal is going to
be, beat this agent.
This agent cannot
train against this.
So there's an asymmetry.
The red gets to see the
games and learn from them.
But the teal does not.
So then what
happens naturally is
that if the agent starts
to specialize to void rays,
naturally, the exploiter
will start doing stalkers.
So now, at least this agent
has seen that, hey, there
are very good players
out there that will do
this other unit that beats me.
So it's going to be
exposed to this strategy
and be able to react properly
and even say, run out
of the optimum, which is
to build lots of void rays,
to say, hey, maybe I actually
should also build immortals
if I see that the enemy is doing
lots of stalkers, et cetera.
So this is simplistic.
But I think it gets the idea
of the algorithm we end up
developing intuitively.
In full, what we do
is this in steroids.
So we had many
different agents that
were created with the
sole goal of making
the main agents, the agents we
actually deployed and became
grandmaster against the
global population of players.
So you can imagine we have these
three main agents, one per race.
And then we have
different agents
whose goal is just to make
the main agents stronger.
So that's the whole
multi-agent system we designed.
And the way it works is
actually super simple.
We didn't experiment
a lot with this.
So the main agents
are essentially
playing against
themselves, playing
against the other main
agents, and playing
against the whole
population all the time.
They're playing
against everyone.
I'll get to how that
distribution of everyone
evolves over time.
But then these main exploiter
agents, they will basically say,
hey, start from the prior,
try to beat, let's say,
the three agents
maximally, so just cheat,
cheat in the sense of,
I can train against you,
you cannot train against me.
Develop a policy that eventually
reaches a certain win rate.
When the win rate is
very high, meaning
I exploited you successfully,
only then you say, hey, here
I am, I'm beating you.
I'm a new player in this world.
Deal with it.
So this agent was
secretly training until it
became good at exploiting.
And when it became good,
it dropped a checkpoint.
It showed itself
against the main agents,
which now, all of a sudden,
could play against it.
And it went, and it restarted
the same process again
from the prior.
So over time, you will
find different exploiters
at different stages of training
against the main agent.
And then we also added
league exploiters,
which is the same concept.
But instead of beating
only the main agents,
these agents try to beat
everyone in the population
by finding exploits that
work against everyone,
rather than just the main agent,
which is a bit more like cheese.
So we have main exploiters,
league exploiters, and then,
of course, main agents.
This was very fun to see, like,
the dynamics, the learning
dynamics, very hard
to understand even
in a game, what's
actually going on.
I mean, intuitively, we know.
But lots to do that are left on
the table from these AlphaStar
league, as we call it.
But it was very powerful.
And then over time, we have over
1,000 agents that have different
strengths.
They will beat a previous agent.
But eventually, the
main agents catch up
and beat the exploiters.
So there's all sorts of
interesting win-rate dynamics.
And it can be represented in
this shape of the spinning top,
a little bit.
So the weakest agents here
are highly non-transitive.
There are 30,000 RPS cycles.
That means the cycle length
of non-transitivity is 30,000.
So you can find 30,000 agents--
I believe that's what
it means-- that beat
the next one, the next one,
and so on and so forth.
And as the agents
become stronger,
they start to fully
dominate, which
is also commonly seen, I mean,
in these interesting games.
So that's an analysis.
This is what happens in rock,
paper, scissors to give you
an example, so much more
complex game dynamics.
And then, as I said, it was
very fun to see this happen.
So you would be training and,
all of a sudden, this red agent
is an exploiter that
finds a cheese that's
called cannon rush.
So the blue agent,
that's the main agent,
has not seen this strategy
enough so it can't really
define very well.
But eventually, by now playing
against this red agent that's
now frozen in time and it will
just do the same strategy,
eventually will be able to
defend and so on and so forth,
so with workers, which
is the right reaction,
and scout to find that you've
been, indeed, in this situation
and so on and so forth.
And we saw all sorts of
interesting dynamics as well.
Anyways, there's
lots of cool games
and, hopefully, analysis
that you can see online.
I don't want to talk
about StarCraft too much.
But it's a passion of
mine, as you can see.
But yeah, this was
kind of very critical.
And then in the
results, you could
see that if you only train with
the population still, but only
of main agents--
so just have three agents
playing against each other
and against themselves
in the past,
that's called
fictitious self-play--
you achieve certain strength.
And this core is
not that perfect.
If you play as a human, you
would not be that strong.
I mean, these differences were
probably less than reality.
And we checked
these a little bit.
But it was hard to do these
experiments in the wild.
Then by adding main exploiters,
we became much stronger.
And by adding, on top of
that, league exploiters,
we had the final
system that was robust
against many different
strategies and, of course, very
strong at playing the game.
Now, a couple of details
and then I'll conclude,
is that the path of
learning matters.
And it's so hard to
know how it matters.
Basically, if you
are now an agent
and is exploited very often
or very rarely or initially is
never exploited, I mean,
all these changes, happily,
the policy you end up with
at the end of this process.
So there's lots of details
that are to be worked out,
even from a theory perspective.
But in these games, and with
deep reinforcement learning,
theory is also hard to come by.
And we had a couple of
strategies on how to matchmake.
So I'm the main agent.
There is literally 1,000 agents.
Which should I play against?
So we had two strategies.
One is, play against
the one that beats you
the most, which
is hard opponents.
And the other one is,
play against the one that
you're 50/50.
You're closest to
maximum entropy.
Because if the one
that beats you the most
beats you all the
time, there's not
going to be a learning signal.
So we tried this,
both strategies.
Variance was a little better,
like this one that maximizes,
kind of, that tries to get
to the sweet spot of 50/50.
But also, I mean, this is one
of the many parameters that
tells you that the
process in which you
create these main policies
matters a whole lot.
And then the other
part that was important
is that to generate interesting
counterstrategies or exploiters
or cheeses, having
controllability mattered.
So not only we started
from the prior distribution
that we had trained
in imitation learning
and say, hey, go and
exploit the main agent,
we also were opinionated about
how you should exploit it.
So we would sometimes,
not always, say,
I want you to exploit
the main agent,
but please do it
with this unit type.
Like, I mentioned how
we did this prompting.
So it was kind of tying your
hands behind a little bit,
saying, hey, I want
you to beat me,
but you have to use this unit.
And that added a component of
robustness and diversification
that also help.
So lots of different choices
here, not a lot of time
we had during the project
to fully study these.
But you can see lots of
different possibilities.
And it was very important
to have this diversity
in the main policy.
Of course, in LLMs,
that is trivial.
So they're very profitable.
There's a lot of diversity.
So there's not a problem
at all to think about, hey,
I don't know, solve
this theorem but do it
in Catalan or in Spanish or
do it in very bare bones.
All these things will add
some sort of robustness
to, maybe, new encounters
that you'll find,
meaning new prompts in LLMs
and so on and so forth.
So contrasting is very
exciting, multi-agent ideas
and space with LLMs.
I mean, one difference is
that users are, in general,
collaborative.
It's not a zero-sum
game that we play.
I go online, and I want
to achieve something, get
some information, help me with
some problem that I'm having.
So I'm actually collaborative
with the other agent, right?
So that's an
interesting difference.
That being said, we also
have adversarial users.
I mean, who doesn't like to
find weird failure modes?
And then Twitter
likes are, obviously,
one of the reward signals
that humans like to optimize.
And also more seriously,
eventually, these systems
become closer and closer
to AGI, very powerful.
So you might want to--
them for doing something
that they shouldn't be doing.
So there's going to
be adversariality
as well, trying to go
around how the system is
designed to be used.
So both aspects could use
multi-agent techniques,
such as the one I described
from the AlphaStar league,
differently.
Complexity is massive
compared to even a game
as complex as StarCraft.
So there's no clear reward.
We discussed this.
Prompting is much less clean
than bits of which units should
you build.
Prompting can be vast.
It's natural language.
It's unbounded.
It's very, very interesting,
the amount of complexity
we'll deal with here.
To the extent that even
these LLMs playing StarCraft,
which is a dream of mine--
They can play.
They're not very good--
is actually one of
the many domains.
So you could see a particular
case of current models
is that we might just
instruct them to, hey,
be a very good StarCraft
player, and then
give them control
of the environment
and see what they do.
And in fact, games,
more and more,
are starting to be
reused, turned around,
be used as an evaluation.
There's a Game Arena, I believe,
on Kaggle that is very popular,
for example.
And famously, I think
some of the LLMs
tried to compete Pokemon, et
cetera, so very cool domain
as well to test ideas.
I will say, some amount
of auto-red teaming,
et cetera, has been using
multi-agent techniques.
But I think, overall,
it's still in its infancy.
So there's lots and lots of
research to be done here.
So to conclude this sort of
past and future combination
and, of course, present
of LLMs, I would say,
there's lots pre-LLM agents.
There's lots of gems to learn
from from many different papers
and different problems.
Tool use was discussed.
Architectures, losses,
regularization, value functions,
I mean, lots of things we can
probably revisit very seriously,
and we should.
My strong belief is that
human priors are going
to be part of the path to AGI.
But we need to obviously also
build knowledge and experience
on top of that prior knowledge.
I've seen it succeed
enough times now,
including in AlphaGo, which
also use imitation plus RL that,
I believe, that's
certainly the shortest
path to AGI, although happy
to discuss that if useful.
Then in general, RL or
post-training on top of LLMs
still feels in their infancy
when I think and compare it
to a system like the
AlphaStar system.
We can train on thousands
of steps, maybe,
versus in this
AlphaStar league, we
use 10 to the 10 training steps
in post-training, so vastly
more compute used
in post-training
rather than in pre-training.
Of course, we also
have this issue
that the rewards are
fuzzily specified.
So that is definitely
a challenge.
And last but not least,
multi-agent RL, in whichever way
you can think of creating a
population of users and agents
talking to one another
and really optimize
and train for that, I
think that's very exciting.
And it's going to have,
probably, a new scalability
breakthrough, I can imagine,
in the next few years,
maybe from some of you.